<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Bare metal on HortaCloud</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/</link><description>Recent content in Bare metal on HortaCloud</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Two-server deployment</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/twoserverdeployment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/twoserverdeployment/</guid><description>This document describes the canonical two-server Janelia Workstation deployment for supporting neuron tracing for the MouseLight project at the Janelia Research Campus and other research institutions. This deployment uses Docker Swarm to orchestrate prebuilt containers available on Docker Hub.
Deployment Diagram Hardware Setup The JACS backend consists of several services which need to be deployed on server hardware. We have tested the following configuration:
Two Dell PowerEdge R740XD Servers Each server has 40 cores (e.</description></item><item><title>Three-server deployment</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/fulldeployment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/fulldeployment/</guid><description>This document describes the full three-server Janelia Workstation deployment for supporting both FlyLight and MouseLight at Janelia Research Campus. This deployment uses Docker Swarm to orchestrate containers available on Docker Hub.
Multiple environments are supported with this deployment:
prod dev Deployment Diagram Hardware Setup This guide assumes that you have three high-end servers which can be dedicated to running Docker Swarm. We use 40-core servers with at least 192 GB of RAM.</description></item><item><title>Installing Docker</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/installingdocker/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/installingdocker/</guid><description>To install Docker on a server running Oracle Linux 8, some special configuration is needed. Much of this comes from the official documentation.
Prerequisites First, make sure that Docker isn’t already installed:
yum list installed | grep docker Remove any existing installations before proceeding.
Ensure that /opt (or whatever disk is to be used for Docker data) is formatted with the d_type option. You can find out like this:
$ xfs_info /opt meta-data=/dev/mapper/vg0-lv_opt isize=512 agcount=4, agsize=5701632 blks = sectsz=4096 attr=2, projid32bit=1 = crc=1 finobt=0 spinodes=0 data = bsize=4096 blocks=22806528, imaxpct=25 = sunit=0 swidth=0 blks naming =version 2 bsize=4096 ascii-ci=0 ftype=1 log =internal bsize=4096 blocks=11136, version=2 = sectsz=4096 sunit=1 blks, lazy-count=1 realtime =none extsz=4096 blocks=0, rtextents=0 If the above says ftype=0, then the filesystem will need to be recreated (reference).</description></item><item><title>Deploying JACS</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/swarmdeployment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/swarmdeployment/</guid><description>This document assumes that you have downloaded and configured the installer according to one of the deployment guides.
The following steps are common to all Docker Swarm deployments of the Workstation.
Initialize Filesystems The first step is to initialize the filesystems on all your Swarm systems. On each server, ensure that your REDUNDANT_STORAGE (default: /opt/jacs), NON_REDUNDANT_STORAGE (default: /data) directories exist and can be written to by your UNAME:GNAME user (default: docker-nobody).</description></item><item><title>Deploying ELK</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/elkdeployment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/elkdeployment/</guid><description>Currently ELK is only available in a swarm deployment because of how the ELK stack is configured.
Most of the set up necessary for ELK - configuration files and/or data directories - is already done as part of filesystem initialization performed while executing:
./manage.sh init-filesystems The current ELK data directories are created on /data/ directory so this directory must exist.
One manual step is to set the vm.max_map_count value required for running elasticsearch.</description></item><item><title>Self-signed Certificates</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/selfsignedcerts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/selfsignedcerts/</guid><description>A self-signed certificate is automatically generated during the init-filesystem step of a jacs-cm installation. For production use, it is recommended that you replace this certificate with a real one. The self-signed certificate is less secure, and it requires some extra steps to get working.
In order to connect to https://HOST1, you need to accept the certificate in the browser. This differs by browser.
Then, in order to allow the Workstation to accept the certificate, it needs to be added to Java&amp;rsquo;s keystore.</description></item><item><title>Storage volumes</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/storagevolumes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/storagevolumes/</guid><description>The Workstation/JACS system relies on JADE for its storage API.
Adding a new Storage Volume Add bootstrap to the JADE configuration
On HOST1, edit /opt/jacs/config/jade/config.properties and add a block for your new volume, for example:
StorageVolume.s3data.RootDir=/s3data StorageVolume.s3data.VirtualPath=/s3jade StorageVolume.s3data.Shared=true StorageVolume.s3data.Tags=aws,cloud StorageVolume.s3data.VolumePermissions=READ,WRITE,DELETE The properties configure the volume as follows:
RootDir: defines the actual path to the data on disk VirtualPath: optionally defines a virtual path which is mapped to the actual path Shared: true if the volume should be accessible to all volumes Tags: tags used by applications to find appropriate volumes VolumePermissions: list of operations that JADE can execute (READ,WRITE,DELETE) Also add your volume to StorageAgent.</description></item><item><title>Data import</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/dataimport/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/dataimport/</guid><description>In principle, any 3d volumetric data can be imported into the MouseLight Workstation. At this moment we only provide some very basic tools for converting only TIFF format images into the expected format on disk. Another limitation of the current tools is that the entire volume must be in a single tiff file (per channel)
The imagery for MouseLight Workstation is a directory containing TIFF and KTX images organized into octrees.</description></item><item><title>Troubleshooting</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/troubleshooting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/bare_metal/troubleshooting/</guid><description>Docker These are some useful commands for troubleshooting Docker:
View logs for Docker daemon
sudo journalctl -fu docker Restart the Docker daemon
sudo systemctl restart docker Remove all Docker objects, including unused containers/networks/etc.
sudo docker system prune -a Swarm GUI If you would like to see the Swarm&amp;rsquo;s status in a web-based GUI, we recommend installing Swarmpit. It&amp;rsquo;s a single command to deploy, and it works well with the JACS stack.</description></item></channel></rss>