<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>AWS on HortaCloud</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/</link><description>Recent content in AWS on HortaCloud</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Costs</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/costs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/costs/</guid><description>Deploying this system on Amazon Web Services (AWS) incurs a monthly cost for AWS service usage.
In particular, the cost breakdown is roughly:
$382/mo - Per user costs for running the Horta client on AppStream $277/mo - Back-end services running on EC2 (with Savings Plan) $76/mo - Storage (3 TB) for one sample image on S3 $34/mo - Virtual Private Cloud (VPC) Therefore, the minimum total cost per month for a single user would be about $770 ($9,237/year).</description></item><item><title>Deployment</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/deployment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/deployment/</guid><description>The deployment uses AWS CDK to create AWS resources on your AWS account as shown in the diagram below. All services run in a secured Virtual Private Cloud (VPC).
Install prerequisites You should have node &amp;gt; v16 installed on your local machine. We recommend using nvm to install and activate this version of node.
Install AWS CLI AWS CDK requires AWS CLI to be installed and configured on the computer from which one runs the deployment procedure.</description></item><item><title>Backup &amp; Restore</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/backups/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/backups/</guid><description>System backup The system can be configured to take nightly backups. All it is needed is to specify a writeable bucket (HORTA_BACKUP_BUCKET) that will hold the backups. You can also specify the base prefix for the backups using HORTA_BACKUP_FOLDER. If this is not specified the prefix will default to &amp;ldquo;/hortacloud/backups&amp;rdquo;.
Currently the backup contains the Cognito users and the Mongo database (user-generated metadata and tracing data). Each backup will be stored in a timestamp (with format &amp;ldquo;yyyyMMddHHmmss&amp;rdquo;) folder under the base backup prefix.</description></item><item><title>Upgrading</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/upgrading/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/upgrading/</guid><description>There are two ways to upgrade to a new version of the code: Full Upgrade and Incremental Upgrade.
Full Upgrade This method backs up all of the data, removes the existing HortaCloud stack, installs a new version from scratch, and restores the data. This is currently the most automated way to upgrade, and requires the least amount of effort.
Backup your data First, ensure that you have a recent data backup.</description></item><item><title>Data Import</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/data/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/data/</guid><description>Adding the MouseLight Open Data The MouseLight project at Janelia has made available the complete imagery and neuron tracing annotations for its published data sets on the AWS Open Data Registry.
You can easily make these available in your own HortaCloud instance by creating a Synchronized Folder which points to /s3data/janelia-mouselight-data.
Adding a single volume A Horta Sample is an object representing a single 3D volume that can be visualized and traced with Horta.</description></item><item><title>Troubleshooting</title><link>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/troubleshooting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hortacloud.janelia.org/docs/administration/aws/troubleshooting/</guid><description>No user can login to the workstation We have seen this behavior if the &amp;ldquo;/data&amp;rdquo; volume ran out of space. You can check this by connecting to the EC2 instance running the JACS stack and running df -h /data.
If the disk is full you, you can try to find anything that could be removed but if the limit was reached because the size your data you really have to resize the volume.</description></item></channel></rss>